<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the commissioners of the General Assembly to the whole kirk and kingdome of Scotland concerning present dangers and duties relating to the covenant and religion.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A33092</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C4218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25372</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08940632</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08940632</idno>
            <idno type="VID">42032</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A33092)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42032)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1279:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the commissioners of the General Assembly to the whole kirk and kingdome of Scotland concerning present dangers and duties relating to the covenant and religion.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Evan Tyler ;</publisher>
                  <publisher>Re-printed for Robert Bostock,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42032:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:42032:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE COMMISSIONERS OF THE GENERAL ASSEMBLY, To the whole Kirk and Kingdome of SCOTLAND,</p>
            <p>CONCERNING Preſent dangers, and duties relating to the <hi>Covenant</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty: And re-printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Robert Boſtock,</hi> at the Kings Head in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:42032:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42032:2"/>
            <head>Edinb. <hi>1</hi> Martii, <hi>1648.</hi> Poſt Meridiem.</head>
            <head>A Declaration of the Commiſsioners of the General Aſſembly to the whole Kirk and Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> concerning preſent dangers, and duties relating to the COVENANT and RELIGION.</head>
            <p>IF in a time of ſo great and imminent danger to Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and the Cauſe of God, the Trumpet in Zion ſhould give no certain ſound, nor the watch-mens Tower any ſeaſonable warning, it might be juſtly charged upon us as a ſinful neglect of duty, and the blood of many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſouls might be required at our hands. Therefore ſo far as we have diſcovered the dangerous plots and ſnares of the malicious and crafty adverſaries of this Cauſe, we ſhall freely and faithfully make the ſame known; truſting that all who would not make ſhipwrack of faith and a good conſcience, will carefully avoid as well hid as manifeſt rocks, when they are warned of them.</p>
            <p>After the Solemn League and Covenant of the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms had ſo proſpered againſt the enemies and oppoſers thereof, as made them deſpair of overthrowing it in any ſuch way of a direct oppoſition; they begun with much wit and induſtry to endeavour a dividing of the ends of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and an altering of the firſt principle and ſtate of the Cauſe. Upon the one hand, the Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42032:3"/>as is formerly repreſented by the late General Aſſembly, in their Declaration to their Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> and by our Remonſtrance to the Committee of Eſtates of the 13 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> laſt) have by fraud and violence endeavoured the ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Religion; whoſe exorbitant inſolency, being now in Arms, is ſo unſupportable, that no man can doubt but all the Articles of the Covenant are in danger by them; the vile Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, wicked Hereſies, and intolerable Blaſphemies daily growing amongſt them, can hardly be reckoned up; all which are mightily aggredged by the lawleſſe and Godleſſe tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof: And leſt Parliamentary authority ſhould curb this monſtrous inſolency, they have not onely refuſed Orders for diſbanding, but have forced Orders for their own ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and do over-rule Parliament, King, City, and Country, to the trampling under foot all Government Civil and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical, and to the terrour, oppreſſion, and apparent ruine of all the truely godly, and ſound lovers of the Solemn League and Covenant. On the other hand, the Prelatical and Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnant party have catched at and ſtudied to make advantage of ſome parts and clauſes of the Covenant, without keeping all the links of that golden chain faſt together.</p>
            <p>This deſigne of receding from the former principles, and ſtating the publike Cauſe otherwiſe then it was ſtated by both Kingdoms when they joyned in Covenant and Arms, may be abundantly diſcovered by two inſtances: Firſt, the deſigne hath been ſo faſt and ſo far driven on, that although the fourth Article of the League and Covenant was clearly framed and intended againſt the Malignant party; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there was one expreſſe Article in the Treaty between the Kingdoms for ſwearing and ſubſcribing the League and Covenant by both Kingdoms, as a more neer tie and conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of both, for their defence againſt the Popiſh, Prelatical
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42032:3"/>and Malignant party and their adherents; And although in the Declarations of both Kingdoms in the yeer 1643, it was declared that all ſuch as would not ſpeedily take the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and joyn with all their power in the defence of this Cauſe, are to be cenſured and puniſhed as profeſſed <hi>Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and <hi>Malignants;</hi> Yet ſome are not aſhamed to plead for the Malignant party, as if they were friends rather then enemies to this cauſe, and as none were now to be looked upon as dangerous enemies to the Cauſe, but the Sectaries onely; whereas the word of God and the experience of former times not onely teacheth us to beware of dangers from the fraud, as well as the force, from the plots as well as from the power of enemies; but alſo ſetteth before us ſad examples of great unexpected miſeries, and miſchiefs brought upon the people of God, from enemies once broken and quaſhed, when they got again the power of the ſword, &amp; opportunity to act what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever cruelties their inveterate malice and enraged ſpirits put them upon.</p>
            <p>The other inſtance is, that although in the Covenant, the duty of preſerving and defending the Kings Majeſties perſon and authority be joyned with &amp; ſubbardinate unto the duty of preſerving and defending the true Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms; and although from the beginning of this Cauſe, the good, ſafety and ſecurity of Religion hath been principally ſought after and inſiſted upon: yet ſolicitations, perſwaſions, and endeavours have not been, nor are wanting for his Majeſties reſtitution to the exerciſe of his Royal pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and for eſpouſing his Majeſties quarrell, notwithſtanding his not granting of the publick deſires concerning the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and Religion: And this courſe is clearely contrary to the declared reſolution of the Parliament of this Kingdom, after advice deſired from us, upon the caſe concerning the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42032:4"/>King then propounded to us; And it is no leſſe contrary to the Principles and profeſſions of the Convention and of the Committee of Eſtates, before any ſuch adviſe was deſired or had from us: yea all along, and in the whole courſe of the publick proceedings, the ſetling and ſecuring of Religion hath been ſo much ſtood upon, that Malignants who intended a new ſtate of the cauſe did well perceive how great difficulty, and how ſmall hopes there was of ſatisfying this Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with any thing elſe, while unſatisfied in the point of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; and therefore all poſſible care hath been taken by them whereby to have ſome ſpecious and fair pretences of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction in the buſineſſe of Religion.</p>
            <p>And here, as we do not diſapprove, but highly commend the worthy pains of ſuch as did indeed endeavour to bring the Kings Majeſtiy a greater length, even to give full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in point of Religion; ſo we cannot but take notice of that report which many did lately entertaine and ſpread in this country; namely, that his Majeſty hath given ſatisfaction to the deſires of this Kirk and Kingdome in point of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Religion.</p>
            <p>If his Majeſty had indeed given ſuch ſatisfaction, we ſhould rejoyce at it as much as any; and however ſhall not ceaſe to pray for his Majeſty, that God would give him repentance and remiſſion of ſins, and incline his heart to the love of the true Religion and Reformation, and that his Royal perſon may be preſerved from all harm and violence: And being now (as we formerly remonſtrate on the 13, of <hi>October</hi>) very ſenſible of the preſent danger his Majeſties perſon and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall goverment is in by that prevalent party of Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; We ſhall, ſo far as concerneth the duty of our places and callings, endeavour the preſervation of Monarchicall govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Majeſty, and his Poſterity according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42032:4"/>not being ignorant what confuſion and calamities uſe to attend the change either of the government it ſelf, or of the Royal line. Nevertheleſſe, the country being ſo generally poſſeſſed with ſo dangerous a miſtake, miſunderſtanding of ſo great a buſineſſe; and his Majeſtie himſelf profeſſing in his letter to us, dated at <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Caſtle the 27 of <hi>December</hi> laſt, that he hath reſolved ſo far to agree to the deſires of this Kirk and Kingdom, concerning the Covenant, and ſetling Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as hee is confident ſhall give us ſatisfaction; If now wee ſhould be ſilent, we might be underſtood as tacitely conſenting and acquieſcing: Wee are therefore neceſſitated for undecei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Nation, and for accquitting our ſelves, to declare, that a Narrative of the ſtate of publick affairs having been made to us by thoſe who were entruſted for that effect, and ſince delivered to us in writing, Wee have more eſpecially taken to our ſerious thoughts ſo much of that Narrative as was from His Majeſty made known unto us, as his reſolutions for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in point of Religion. The firſt Article whereof is as followeth:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>For the Covenant, His Majeſty giving beleef to the profeſsions of thoſe who have entred into the League and Covenant, and that their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions are reall for preſervation of His Majeſties Perſon, according to their allegeance, and no ways to diminiſh his juſt Power and Greatneſſe, is content, ſo ſoon as he can with freedom, honour and ſafety be preſent in a free Parliament, to confirm the ſaid League and Covenant by Act of Parliament in both Kingdoms, for ſecurity of all thoſe who have taken, or ſhall take the ſaid Covenant: Provided that none who is unwilling ſhall be constrained to take it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Article hath nothing in it of His Majeſties affection to, or liking and approbation of the Covenant, but onely what he is content to yeeld in order to his own intereſt. Yea, an Act of Parliament for ſecurity of thoſe who have taken, or ſhal take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42032:5"/>the Covenant, doth or may ſuppoſe ſome fault, or ſomewhat juſtly challengable in the taking of the Covenant, which need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth an Act of Indemnity. Next, the offer is but conditionall, and hath in the boſom of it a complication of ſuch and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conditions, as might open a door to ſome evaſion or other, by multiplying exceptions, difficulties, and various notions, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning the profeſſions of thoſe who have entred into the League &amp; Covenant, or concerning His Majeſties juſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and greatneſſe, or concerning his freedom, honour and ſafety, or concerning a free Parliament. And although the conceſſion were certain and abſolute, it amounts to no more but to a lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of the Covenant arbitrary; which is contrary to the Acts of the Generall Aſſembly and Parliament in this Kingdom, to the Declaration of both Kingdoms before cited, and to one of the chief Propoſitions of Religion once agreed upon by both Kingdoms, for a ſafe and wel grounded Peace; <hi>viz.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition concerning His Majeſties (wearing and ſigning of the League and Covenant, and enjoyning by Act of Parliament in both Kingdoms the taking thereof by all the Subjects in the three Kingdoms, with ſuch penalties as ſhall be agreed upon by both Kingdoms: So that the firſt Article of His Majeſties offer is a moſt manifeſt altering of the State of this cauſe; It is alſo a ſtrengthening of the hearts and hands both of the Sectaries, and of the Malignant Party, a partaking and conniving at the ſin of all thoſe in the three Kingdoms who have refuſed, or ſhall refuſe to enter into the League &amp; Covenant, an introducing of a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality in this cauſe which ſo much concerneth the glory God, the good of the Kingdom, and the honour of the King. And therefore wee have judged this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle not onely unſatisfactory, but deſtructive to the Covenant. Neither are wee moved with that objection which is hinted concerning the conſtraining or enforcing men conſciences:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42032:5"/>They refuſe a neceſſary duty who refuſe to take the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; and the penalty or puniſhment of ſuch refuſall is no conſtraining of the Conſcience, more then the penalty or puniſhment of a Subject who refuſeth to take the Oath of Allegiance is a conſtraining of the conſcience to Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, or more then the puniſhment of Idolaters, Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and Seducers, mentioned ſo often in Scripture, can be called a conſtraining of the conſcience to the fear of God.</p>
            <p>The words of the ſecond Article are theſe:</p>
            <p>His Majeſty will likewiſe confirm by Act of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> Presbyteriall Government, the Directory for Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and Aſſembly of Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> for three years, ſo that his Majeſty and his houſhold be not hindered from uſing that form of Divine Service he hath formerly pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed; and that a free debate and conſultation be had with the Divines at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (twenty of his Majeſties nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation being added unto them) and with ſuch as ſhal be ſent from the Church of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereby it may be determined by his Majeſtie and the two Houſes how the Church Government after the three years ſhall be fully eſtabliſhed according to the Word of God.</p>
            <p>For ought we know the conditions couched in the firſt Article are alſo to be underſtood in this and the following Articles: However this ſecond Article as it is but the ſame in ſubſtance with ſome of his Majeſties conceſſions in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Meſſages, ſo that which is propoſed in it, is but a To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration of Presbyterial Government in <hi>England,</hi> and that but for three years, and is a direct allowance, at leaſt of the book of Common-Prayer in his Majeſties Houſhold: And moreover by the ſecond Article not only a door is left open for re-eſtabliſhing Prelacy and the Service Book, But the happy progreſs already made in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and Uniformitie of Religion according to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42032:6"/>Covenant in a Confeſſion of Faith, Directorie of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Form of Church Government and Catechiſm is ſet aſide as ſo much loſt labour, in order to a future ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Free debate with any of the Prelaticall party no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated by his Majeſtie (when there was any ſuch occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion) hath not been declined: But we have great cauſe to be tender of unſetling and razing a good foundation alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die laid in the work of Reformation. And whereas his Majeſtie will have it determined by himſelf, and the two Houſes, how the Church Government after the ſaid three years ſhall be eſtabliſhed according to the Word of God: This doth at once cut off three of the moſt materiall and moſt neceſſary Propoſitions concerning Religion former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed upon by both Kingdoms, and from both tendred to his Majeſtie (though ſome of them be now laid aſide by the two Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi>) namely, The third Propoſition, for aboliſhing Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. The fifth Propoſition, That Reformation of Religion according to the Covenant be ſetled by Act of Parliament, in ſuch manner as both houſes have agreed, or ſhall agree upon after conſultation had with the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines; And the ſixth Propoſition, That ſuch unity and uniformitie in Religion according to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as after conſultation had with the Divines of both Kingdoms, aſſembled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> is, or ſhall be joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly agreed by both Houſes of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and by the Church and Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Acts of Parliament of both Kingdoms reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively. Of which three Propoſitions, there can be no hopes as to his Majeſties conſent or concurrence) if the offer now made concerning a determination by his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and the two Houſes, be compared with his Majeſties claiming of a negative voyce, and with his Meſſage of <hi>Nov.</hi> 16. in which he declared that both in Relation as he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42032:6"/>is a Chriſtian, and as a King, he cannot give his conſent to the aboliſhing Archbiſhops, Biſhops, &amp;c. Beleeving that this order was placed in the Church by the Apoſtles themſelves, and that his Majeſty is alſo bound by his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronation Oath to maintain it. And this meſſage of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember</hi> 16. His Majeſtie adhereth unto, in his Anſwer to the Bills and Propoſitions preſented to him at <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Caſtle; which Anſwer is dated <hi>December</hi> 28. and ſo after his Majeſties Letter to us. Upon theſe and the like conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations we have found the ſaid ſecond Article of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties offers in point of Religion to be deſtructive to Presbyteriall Government, the Directorie of Worſhip, and the uniformitie intended according to the Covenant.</p>
            <p>For the third Article delivered to us in theſe words. <hi>And for ſuppreſsing of Schiſm and Hereſies, his Majeſtie is content and moſt willing that an effectual courſe be taken by Act of Parliament, and all other wayes needfull and expedient for ſuppreſsing the opinions and practiſes of Antitrinitarians, Arrians, Socinians, Antiſcripturiſts, Antinomians, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, Arminians, Familiſts, Browniſts, Separatiſts, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents, Libertines, and Seekers, and generally for ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all Blaſphemie, Hereſie, Schiſm, and all ſuch ſcandalous doctrine or practiſes as are contrary to the light of nature, or to the known principles of Christianity (whether concerning faith, worſhip, or converſation) or to the power of Godlineſs, or which may be deſtructive to Order or Government, or to the peace of Church or Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As we do approve of the Suppreſſion of the particular Hereſies and Schiſmes enumerated in his Majeſties offer; So we ſee not how it can be reconciled with his Majeſties Meſſage of <hi>November</hi> 16. in which there was a conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all ſuch as differ from Presbyteriall Government: And do further find the Article dangerous and defective in omitting Eraſtianiſm, and other dangerous errours,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42032:7"/>eſpecially Popery and Prelacy, which may prove deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive to the Covenant, in miniſtring the occaſion to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and Prelates to plead for a toleration; although the Covenant bind us to endeavour the extirpation both of Popery and Prelacy.</p>
            <p>Having now diſcovered the ſnares and dangers, we ſhall in the next place moſt humbly and ſeriouſly propoſe and recommend ſome wholſom, ſeaſonable and pious counſels to all the Members of this Church and Kingdom, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the Honorable and High Court of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and to the Brethren of the Miniſtry, which may alſo ſerve to expreſs our ſenſe concerning the whole matter contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that narrative, delivered to us in writing, ſo far as is competent and fit for us to give any judgment thereupon.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all we exhort all and every one to make more conſcience of endeavouring a reall Reformation of themſelves and their Families, and of the places in which they live then ever yet they have done; to be more ſerious in ſearching their hearts, conſidering their ways, and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themſelves from all filthineſs of the fleſh and ſpirit to perfect holineſs in the fear of God; to oppoſe wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and prophaneneſs, promote the power and practiſe of Godlineſs, and to be deeply humbled before the Lord for neglecting theſe things ſo much and ſo long; with all em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying and improving Chriſts al-ſufficiency, and ſtriving to exerciſe faith in him for the grace of mortification and ſanctification, as well as for remiſſion of ſins and peace with God; that being implanted and rooted in him, we may grow up as trees of Righteouſneſs, the planting of the Lord that he may be glorified; for without amendment of life, and bringing forth of better fruit, the fierce wrath of the Lord cannot turn away from us.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as men deſire they may not be led into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but may be guided in ſafe and right paths, in the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42032:7"/>midſt of ſo great difficulties; Let them avoid the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and counſel of the ungodly, whereby even good men have been oft times moſt dangerouſly inſnared; Let all that fear God chooſe the Teſtimonies of the Lord for their counſellors, be much in prayer, and ſearching the mind of God in his word without leaning to their own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, or conſulting with fleſh and blood in caſes of conſcience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſeeing it is no act of wiſdom but of folly, ſo to ſhun one danger as to run upon another as bad or worſe; Let us therefore avoid enemies, and beware of dangers on all hands: We cannot ſee but the cauſe of God, the true Religion, the Covenant, Presbyteriall Government, this Church and Kingdom, and whatſoever is deareſt to us wil be in as great danger, if the Prelatical party prevail; as now they are in by the power and prevalency of Sectaries in <hi>England,</hi> who have made the Covenant and begun Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation to be laid aſide and hindered the promoting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So that there is a neceſſity to be apprehenſive of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and attentive to remedies on both ſides, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of compliance with, and connivance at Sectaries up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the one hand, and Malignants upon the other.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, when we ſpeak of Malignants, we deſire that the diſtinction may be remembered, which was made in the ſolemn Warning to the Kingdom from the Generall Aſſembly in <hi>February</hi> 1645. <hi>Viz.</hi> That the cauſe is in very great danger from two ſorts of Malignant enemies: Firſt, from ſuch as have openly diſplayed a Bannar, or joyned in Arms and profeſſed Hoſtility againſt the cauſe, and ſuch as adhered thereunto: Secondly, from ſecret Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, Diſcovenanters, and boſom Enemies. This ſecond ſort may be ſtill known by ſome Characters, given both at that time and before that time; as by their ſlandering
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42032:8"/>or cenſuring the Covenant of the three Kingdoms and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition into <hi>England,</hi> in the year 1643, as not neceſſary for the good of Religion, or ſafety of this Kingdom, or as tending to the diminution of the Kings juſt power and greatneſs, by their confounding of the Kings Power and juſt Authority, with the pretence and abuſe thereof by Commiſſions, Warrants or Letters procured from his Majeſty by the enemies of this cauſe and Covenant; as if none were faithful and loyal to the King, who oppoſe ſuch men and their ways; by their ſpleen, malice and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies againſt ſuch as God hath made eminently inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall in this cauſe, and who reſolve to be conſtant to the end in their firſt Principles; as if ſuch men were the Kings ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who are moſt zealous for the good and ſafety of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; by their commending, juſtifying or excuſing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther known Malignants, and by their converſing or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communing with excommunicate Delinquents. Unto which Characters time and experience give us occaſion to add ſome others, as namely, their unwillingneſs and decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to reckon Malignants among the enemies of this cauſe, from whom danger is to be apprehended; Their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning and dividing the duty of endeavouring the Kings Majeſties preſervation and reſtitution, from the duty of preſerving, defending, ſetling and ſecuring Religion: As if we might and ought to purſue the former without the latter, while both are in danger; Their maligning of, and uttering malicious words againſt faithfull and zealous Miniſters, and againſt this meeting and Judicatory, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Generall Aſſembly: Laſtly, their crying up or down of parties or perſons, and even of the Sectaries themſelves according as they have more or leſs hopes of advantage from them to their own deſigns. For 'tis not long ſince ſuch men made light account of any dangers, which were apprehended from the prevalent faction of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42032:8"/>the Sectaries in <hi>England;</hi> There being then ſome hopes of a compliance and combination between them and the Malignants: which is an infallible demonſtration that ſuch mens pretended Zeal againſt thoſe Sectaries now is not from the right Principle. Wherefore, let all ſuch dangerous perſons, as we have here deciphered and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, be carefully obſerved and avoided, as men would keep themſelves pure, and free of ſnares: And let Presbyteries be diligent to diſcover, try and cenſure any of this kind in their bounds, that they may be able herein to give a good account of their diligence; As alſo, that they be careful to diſcover, try and cenſure any trafficking Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and all ſuch as favour their opinions and ways.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Though we eſteem that prevalent Faction of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries, with their abbetters and adherents, Preſumptuous and Malicious enemies to Religion, King and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Yet we hold it is our duty to labour to remove and prevent all occaſions <hi>of jealouſies and ſuſpitions betwixt the Kingdoms, and do or ſay nothing that may breed miſunderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, break off correſpondence, weaken the confidence, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe the Union and Peace betwixt the two Kingdoms, ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily eſtabliſhed in his Majeſties preſence, and with his Royall conſent in both Parliaments;</hi> A caution as neceſſary now, as when it was given above five years ago in a Warning from the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſſembly, met in this ſame place, <hi>January</hi> the fourth, 1643. And Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally we deſire that all the Articles and clauſes of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn League and Covenant may be kept inſeparably, and inviolably linked together, and that there may be great tenderneſs and care to avoid every thing which may be interpreted as a contradicting or abandoning of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Principles, Proceedings, Petitions, Proteſtations, Remonſtrances and Declarations of this Kirk and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in the purſuance of this cauſe; and more eſpecially
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42032:9"/>to take good heed that <hi>Scotlands</hi> deſires, do not mount higher for the King, and fall lower in the point of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then they were at our firſt undertaking and ingage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in this cauſe.</p>
            <p>Finally, we do moſt ſeriouſly obteſt all the people of God in this Nation, and eſpecially the Eſtates of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by their love to the cauſe of God, by their ſolemn Vows and Covenants, by their firſt principles and profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by their former zeal and ſincerity, by the many bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of God, and his great works done for us when our zeal and integritie was greateſt in this cauſe, and by all the curſes and judgements of God which his Word denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth againſt back ſliders and Covenant-breakers, that they may all the dayes of their lives continue firm, ſtedfaſt, and faithfull in their Covenant with God, and one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make good their former profeſſions in a time of tentation and difficultie, without waving or falling off to the right hand, or to the left, and as many as walk accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this rule peace be on them and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:42032:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
